thanks for joining me here. I'm nervous.
So that's great
because it means I will finish on time.
I'm going to go too fast.
I'm going to present on quilt poems
encoding craft traditions
as generative poetry.
And I'm going to start
by talking a little bit about quilts.
I should mention I'm an artist,
a programmer, and an educator.
I'm based in New York City,
and you can find out
more about my projects at this website.
I'll also link to these slides and my
project online at the end of the talk.
I'm going to start in Pennsylvania.
I'm from Philadelphia.
And what we're looking at is a photograph.
This is a photograph of the side of a barn
in Amish country, just a few hours
outside of Philly.
And these are paintings of Amish quilts.
These are quilt blocks
on the side of a barn.
And then I'm going to jump to a picture
of an old studio of mine
with some in-progress quilts of my own.
You see one
hanging down in the top center.
There's one on the right, one on the floor
that is in some scraps.
And then my sewing machine on the left.
That's a five, five, five machine.
And it's a pretty accurate representation
of what my studio often looks like.
And here's
some of the quilts that I've made.
And I just also want to kind of talk
about what a quilt is and define it.
So quilts are made of scraps of fabric.
They in many communities have often
been made of old clothing, particularly
in communities where they might not
have had access to lots of resources.
They were.
They served several uses,
including keeping you warm.
But they could also, of course,
be considered works of works of art.
They could be their craft.
They are a decoration.
There are lots of different things.
These are some of my own artworks
that I made over a decade ago.
This is one of them that I made called
Stop the Initiative.
On the right side
you can see a particular quilt pattern.
This is a variation on the Log
cabin quilt pattern,
and it's made up of smaller scraps
that are pieced together when you connect
parts of scraps of fabric.
That's called piecing.
Once you get to an entire
front piece, that's entire front,
that's made up of all the pieces,
you connect it to a back and you.
So through the entire thing
that's called quilting.
So a quilt is both
the name for the object.
It's and quilting
is also the process of sewing through it.
There are two communities
I'm going to reference today
that are celebrated quilt makers,
and one is the Jes Ben
quilt
making community from G's Bend in Georgia.
I just picked a few. On the left.
You see two examples of quilts
from that community,
and on the right
you actually see some quilt makers
that are doing that process of quilting,
sewing through a house top pattern
quilt through the batting, which is like
the stuffing in the center to the back.
This
is maybe representative of what
we might think of as like a quilters, B
where these women are getting together
at the end of where
maybe a single quilter made the front,
and then a community is sewing
the whole thing
together, is quilting it together.
I mentioned before the Amish quilt
making community, and these are three
different representative examples of Amish
quilt making.
These are Roman bars pattern on the left,
a simpler bars
pattern in the center, and on the right
a log cabin quilt variation.
Okay, now I'm going to jump to something
completely different for a second,
and then we'll wind our way back there.
Nano Jen Mo many people might be familiar
with, but if you're not, this is an idea
from the programmer creative
practitioner scholar Darius Kazemi.
Based off of the definition
of National Novel Writing Month
NaNoWriMo, that a novels
written is a minimum of 50,000 words,
Darius came up with the idea
that you could, if you generated a novel
or a book or a collection of words,
essentially of 50,000 words.
That would be enough to satisfy
the minimum requirements of nano Mo.
And ever since, every year
a number of people generate
novels and stories each November.
So I participated maybe 7 or 8 times.
And in 2024.
I worked on quilt poems,
where it's at least.
When I began working on this,
I looked for patterns
of traditional patchwork quilting
as a data set, and I did not find that.
So there's lots of data sets for weaving
and many other textile practices,
but I did not find quilting.
So first, just based off of my own
background in quilting,
I know enough to be able
to identify patterns.
But then I also consulted books
from the Internet Archive,
from libraries, from my own collection
to and try to assemble.
Okay, what's a collection
of different types of quilts?
And then my next step was
what would it look like to encode them
into data, data that I could use
to to create new projects?
I had been
using Puzzle Script,
which is a very minimal game
engine where sprites are created
out of five by five grids.
And inspired by that, I tried to find
the lowest resolution I could.
I could encode of a quilt five by five
didn't do it for me.
I couldn't quite make recognizable data
sets of five by five at least,
that were that were different enough
and that and satisfied my my interest.
I found that an eight by eight
grid was able to encode
the the 28 or so quilt
patterns that I had collected
or had listed.
What you see here is just a small subset
of the quilt patterns.
And these numbers are stand
ins for color blocks.
So my smallest pixel, you could say,
or my smallest piece
or block is a single block of color.
Each of these numbers
represent a different color,
and there can be eight
total colors in a quilt.
And these are the constraints
that I place.
Now, I'm not saying that
this is how all quilt making works.
On the right side
you can see one of the G's Bend quilts.
This is in a household.
Sorry, a house top pattern.
On the left you can see my eight
by eight representation
of the house top pattern.
So for example, here's a strip on the top
and the same strip color
going down on the left.
On the right
you see one another strip color,
and then on the bottom
and you can see that kind of spiraling in.
I did a lot of experiments
where essentially I would have,
you know, we're looking at these eight
by eight grids instead of having a number
represent
a color in my blocks of quilt poems,
I had words from a corpus
randomly selected
through procedural generation
that I wrote in Lua, and
at first I tried it
with a combination of words and colors.
You can see here this house top quilt
pattern that we saw in the previous slide.
Here's an example of that.
But then I actually remove the colors
and just let the words stand on their own.
And here's some examples
that were generated using this process.
This is the Liver Man bullseye quilt.
For example.
Here's a bars quilt polka fire
bars quilt.
And so I'm just going to kind of show
a few examples in a little bit
more detail.
For example, here's
the chairman Cringe Amish Bars quilt
I generated this one yesterday.
I'm going to show the spill
kerchief little coins
quilt in the little coins pattern.
Basically,
you have single scraps of fabric
that gets sewn into a much larger block.
That's all one color.
So here our one color is still in.
The little blocks are kerchief.
I actually don't know how to say
this word.
Presser. Pasteboard.
Anger.
Seducer.
Here's a God's eye quilt pattern.
Logical. True.
God's eye quilt.
Okay, so
based off of now, you've seen a little bit
of how these quilts get assembled.
Oh sorry.
I'm going to show one more.
This is the Die Polluter
Amish Bars variation quilt,
this one I generated yesterday as well.
You can see the different bars
running down the page.
These are double thick bars
here for Polluter and Exquisite.
And we have single column for stick
and pentoxide.
After participating in nano
and generating my PDF,
I decided I wanted to see this in person.
So I created a number of chapbooks
of generated quilt poems,
did two editions of 50 I think it was.
And then I also decided
to choose another format.
I have what I call the Daily Quilt Poem,
which is once a day.
You can see a new well.
You can see at any time
you visit the website, but
it changes
once a day to show a new daily quilt poem.
This one I think was from two days ago.
This is smoke big log cabin quilt.
I've also been trying
other variations working with color.
I think in my next steps.
I just wanted to mention where I'm
going with this small project now
trying out multiple grid sizes
eight by eight felt productive,
but I feel like I want to go larger
working with additional corpora.
I didn't really get deep into
where my corpus of text came from.
In addition of coming from texts
that I collected on quilting,
I also chose a variety of corpora
from Darius
Kazemi corpora repository.
I want to add more quilt patterns.
And lastly, I want to build
in some variation techniques almost.
I would think of this similar
to glitching, where parts of a quilt might
get changed or rotated,
because that can often happen,
particularly in
the Gibbon quilt community.
Here are some links to my
quilt patterns, as well as to the code
to reproduce the generating these quilts
I work primarily in Lua,
and I've saved the data within Lua
as well as a as a Lua table set.
Here's my own links.
If you want to get in touch
or ask me questions or find me elsewhere.
I just also wanted to mention briefly
two other things.
I have a podcast called Artisan Hackers,
and I also am working on a creative
coding library that's called L5.
You can find more about both of those on
my website, and we have Mastodon accounts
for those two,
which is my preferred way of staying in
touch with other creative practitioners.
I think that's it. Thanks so much.